 Objectives:

 

    Define a new class where one object represents a table showing the cellular data over many years for different countries.
    Define a Java application that tests the new class.
    Practice using two dimensional arrays.
    Become accustomed to the programming style required for this class.
    Get in the habit of committing your work to your assigned github.com repository.

 

​Material from:

    Program Guidelines from Module.
    Multi-dimensional arrays:
        Chapter 7 and 8 from Liang textbook, 
        Chapter 10 from Wu textbook.
    ​Source Code Control tutorial from Module.

 

Write a new class called CellularData where one object represents a table containing all cellular data for different countries.

    Each object of this class has a two dimensional array named "table" where the row represents a country, and the column represents the number of subscriptions for a specific year. 

    Each object of this class also stores the name of all the countries. Think about how you want to manage this...​
    Recall: If your table holds decimal numbers, then table[x][y] = "USA" is invalid.

    Each object of this class must keep track of the year associated with each column of the table. Is doesn't make sense to have the value in a couple of cells of your table to hold a label (i.e. a value that stands for the year), and the rest to hold the number of subscriptions. So, you must keep track of the year separate from table.
    Hint: The years are consecutive. So, you can just keep track of start or end.

For this and the rest of the programming assignments we will be using Mobile Cellular Data from The World Bank (http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/IT.CEL.SETS.P2/). The data will be in Comma-Separated Value (CSV) format (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comma-separated_values).

For this project, you can just copy and paste data from the CSV file to your test file. We'll go more into what this test file should look like shortly...

For now, let's look at an example of cellular data for 3 different countries from the years 1983 to 1989. The data shows the number of subscriptions per 100 people. 
Country Name,1983,1984,1985,1986,1987,1988,1989
United States,0,0,0.14,0.28,0.5,0.83,1.39
Canada,0,0,0.05,0.23,0.37,0.75,1.26
Mexico,0,0,0,0,0,0,0.01
 
NOTE: If the data was too insignificant then it was not included omitted.
What is insignificant data?
Well, that depends on the authors of the data. However, you can imagine for example if just the president and a few of those around him had a mobile connection (perhaps via Satellite, etc) then the average number of subscriptions will be less than 0.01 per 100 people. But we are digressing...
 
After a couple of steps of manually analyzing the data (via the tedious task of searching, filtering, copying and pasting) I was able to extract an interesting pattern regarding the adoption of cell phones in the masses. For example, can you tell me how many years after we see subscriptions in United States, we start seeing in Mexico?
 
With just 21 pieces of data (3 countries * 7 years), answering the question above is not too difficult. But, imagine if we had to answer similar questions about various countries by manually sifting through the data of 250+ countries over 50+ years. It would not be fun! The goal of this and the following programming assignment is to make this process easier.
 

 

Let's get back to the data. Initially you want to create some test data. To do this, just copy and paste portions of the "cellular.csv" you are interested and create a one-dimensional array out of it.  Instead of assigning the array elements individually, initialize it at the time of declaration. For example, we copied data from the CSV file for United States during seven years starting from 1983. So, we initialize the array usa to:

double[] usa = {0,0,0.14,0.28,0.5,0.83,1.39};

However, your test data must be declared as final so that they are not easy to change.

 

NOTE: Rename the date file to "cellular.csv"

            Etudes tends to add sequence numbers such as "-1" and "-2".

 

 

You must also write a separate class to test your class CellularData. This class will exist in it's own file (as required by Program Guidelines).

The main() below must create the desired output, which is specified in the inline comments.

 

/** Tests class CellularData by creating one object from it and 
  * calling methods on it.
  */
public class TestCellularData {
         public static void main(String[] args) {
                  System.out.println("Part 1 with Partial Data:");
                  final double[] canadaPartial = {0,0,0.05,0.23,0.37,0.75,1.26};
                  final double[] mexicoPartial = {0,0,0,0,0,0,0.01};
                  final double[] usaPartial = {0,0,0.14,0.28,0.5,0.83,1.39};

                  int startingYear = 1983;
                  CellularData datatable;
                  int numRows = 3;
                  int numColumns = canadaPartial.length;

                  datatable = new CellularData(numRows, numColumns, startingYear);
                  datatable.addCountry("canada", canadaPartial);
                  datatable.addCountry("mexico", mexicoPartial);
                  datatable.addCountry("usa", usaPartial);
                  
                  System.out.println(datatable);
                  // Note: The output of your table may be different as long as it's readable
                  // canada        0    0    0.05    0.23    0.37    0.75    1.26    
                  // mexico        0    0    0       0       0       0       0.01    
                  // usa           0    0    0.14    0.28    0.50    0.83    1.39

 

                  System.out.printf("usa (1983 to 1989): %.2f \n", datatable.getNumSubscriptionsInCountryForPeriod("usa",1983,1989));
                  // country is "usa", subscriptions from 1983 to 1989
                  // the output is: 
                  // usa (1983 to 1989): 3.14

                  System.out.printf("mexico (1983 to 1989): %.2f \n", datatable.getNumSubscriptionsInCountryForPeriod("mexico",1983,1989));
                  // country is "mexico", subscriptions from 1960 to 2000
                  // the output is:
                  // mexico (1983 to 1989): 0.01                  
                  // NOTE: in order to get this result, you must test beyond the sample data included here and refer to the CSV file.

                  System.out.printf("canada (1890 to 2000): %.2f \n", datatable.getNumSubscriptionsInCountryForPeriod("canada",1890, 2000));
                  // the output is:
                  // ERROR : requested year 1890  is less than starting year 1893
                  // canada (1890 to 2000): -1.00 

                  
                  // Part 2
                  System.out.println("\n\nPart 2 with All Data:");
                  final double[] canada = {/* refer to the CSV file */};
                  final double[] mexico = {/* refer to the CSV file */};
                  final double[] usa = {/* refer to the CSV file */};

                  startingYear = 1960;
                  numRows = 3;
                  numColumns = canada.length;
        
                  datatable = new CellularData(numRows, numColumns, startingYear);
        
                  datatable.addCountry("canada", canada);
                  datatable.addCountry("mexico", mexico);
                  datatable.addCountry("usa", usa);

                  System.out.println(datatable);
                  // The output of your table. 

                  System.out.printf("usa (1983 to 1989): %.2f \n", datatable.getNumSubscriptionsInCountryForPeriod("usa",1983,1989));
                  // country is "usa", subscriptions from 1983 to 1989
                  // the output is same as Part 1

                  System.out.printf("mexico (1960 to 2000): %.2f \n", datatable.getNumSubscriptionsInCountryForPeriod("mexico",1960,2000));
                  // country is "mexico", subscriptions from 1960 to 2000
                  // the output is: 
                  // mexico (1960 to 2000): 29.62
        
                  System.out.printf("canada (1890 to 2000): %.2f \n", datatable.getNumSubscriptionsInCountryForPeriod("canada",1890, 2000));
                  // testing out-of-bounds data
                  // the output is same as Part 1
         }
} 

 

Testing:

    Add at least two test cases beyond those provided.

    For example: Make sure your implementation can handle more than 3 countries.
    Try modifying the output when the range of years provided is invalid. Currently the output is -1.00, which is not user friendly.  One way is to modify the test file to provide a more user friendly output for all cases where the requested data does not exist.

 

 
 

As always you may create as many additional classes, attributes and methods as you need.

 

In order to receive full credit on this assignment, your program must:

    Follow all Program Guidelines, see Modules for the guidelines.
    Get the correct results when the main() given above is run. NOTE: in order to get this result, you must test beyond the sample data included here and refer to the CSV file.
    Include the following in your lab submission:
        The source code: the listing of your program under the "src" directory;
        Comment all classes and all methods. Then, generate Javadocs and include it in your submission. 
        Reminder: A brief tutorial on generating Javadocs is included in the Introudctions module section Example Program Submission.
        Run output sample(s): in a plain-text file called RUN.txt
        (For now, the output should be only plain-text);
        A brief description of all files submitted: in a plain-text file called README.txt.
